I'm gonna start the recorder. Is that on hold?
Okay.
Send me a note that the video didn't work on Monday, but
I don't really know what to do about it except keep doing
what I'm doing.
Okay,
we're supposed to be live, hopefully we are.
Do you want me to do it, you do it on you
too?
I have an audio, yeah, the audio works okay. All right, we
are at still at the very beginning of that פרק האישה רבה,
Perek Ha-Ishah Rabbah, which if you may have if you've ever heard
of it before or you noticed yesterday is one of the most
perplexing and complicated פרקים Perakim and particularly in terms of just rabbinic
justice, it's very challenging to understand how this poor woman who seems
to have done everything right ends up so in such bad trouble
that she has to leave both husbands and she doesn't get any
of her rights from these husbands. And so the first thing that
the תלמוד Talmud does, the תלמוד Talmud comes to the conclusion that
what is the story going on in our משנה? Mishna? The story
is initially she got there a single witness came and told her
that her husband was dead. She went to the בית דין Beis
Din and got permission to go and get married.
And therefore at the end because it was based on a single
witness, she has all of these bad things happen to her. But
if she had had two witnesses came and told her her husband
was dead, then we would say that actually she can go back
to her first husband, the initial, the second marriage was nothing and
and so on. So what that tells us says the משנה, Mishna,
says the גמרא, Gemara, is that apparently a single witness is believed.
And not only that, but we see that if a single witness
says אכלת חלב Achalta Chelev and a guy says and somebody and
the person who you accused says לא אכלתי חלב, Lo Achalti Chelev,
which is which is ground for bringing a קרבן, Korban, he's פטור.
Patur. And from this the גמרא Gemara tells us that if he
just just doesn't say anything, that tells us that he would actually
be חייב, Chayav, which means that on the basis of this single
witness we bring a קרבן. Korban. Normally in cases of ספק Safeik
where we're not sure if something happened or not, we would say
it's a אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, it's not a it's not a
חטאת. Chatas. But here it seems you bring a קרבן חטאת, Korban
Chatas, which means that you actually bring an animal which may be
חולין Chulin into the into the Temple, which means that we we
accept that a single witness can actually be believed מדאורייתא. M'doraisa. Which
is extremely surprising. And so on this we're seven lines from the
bottom, the last two words. We say מנא לן? Minalan? Since where
do we where do we learn that a single witness could possibly
be believed
מדאורייתא? M'doraisa? דתניא: Detanya: או הודע אליו חטאתו, O hoda eilav chataso,
ולא שיודיעוהו אחרים. V'lo sheyodiuho acherim. So we bring the פסוק Pasuk
that talks about the קרבן חטאת Korban Chatas and we say he
himself has to know his חטא. Cheit. He has to know that
he's done this this thing. It can't be that somebody somehow made
him know it, somebody else. So we say יכול אף על פי
שאינו מכחישו יהיה פטור. Yachol af al pi she-eino mach'chisho yi'hyeh patur.
So according to that, perhaps even though he doesn't contradict the other
person, perhaps he is if somebody comes and says אכלת חלב Achalta
Chelev and he doesn't contradict, perhaps that would be still פטור Patur
because somebody else came and told him so, maybe that doesn't count
as או הודע אליו. O hoda eilav. תלמוד לומר או הודע אליו,
Talmud lomar o hoda eilav, that he learns of it מכל מקום,
Mikol makom, from any situation.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to start commenting on this. היכי
דמי? Heichi dami? What's the situation where this person learns of it?
אילימא דאתו בי תרי ולא קא מכחיש להו, Ileima de-asu bei trei
v'lo ka mach'chish le-hu, if it's because two witnesses came and he
didn't contradict them, קרא למה לי? Kra lama li? What do I
need a פסוק Pasuk for? Two witnesses is a is an absolute
fact. אלא לאו, Ella lav, rather חד. Chad. וכי לא קא מכחיש
ליה מהימן. V'chi lo ka mach'chish lei meheiman. שמע מינה עד אחד
נאמן. Shema mina eid echad ne'eman. So therefore what must we be
talking about? A single witness, which I must point out seems to
fit with the language of the ברייתא Braisa which says אף על
פי שאינו מכחישו,
Af al
pi she-eino mach'chisho, right, he didn't contradict him as opposed to contradict
them. So it does indeed sound like we're talking about a single
witness and therefore if you don't contradict him you're חייב. Chayav. That
means that the witness must be believed and therefore we say that
a single... the witness is actually believable from the תורה. Torah. The
גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, back up. וממאי דמשום דמהימן? Umimai
demishum de'meiman?
Maybe it's not because of the reliability of the witness we're talking
about. דילמא משום דקשתיק? Dilma mishum de'kashtik?
Maybe it's because this person is not talking, he is quiet. ושתיקה
כהודאה דמיא? Ushtika ke'hoda'ah damya? And silence is the equivalent of acceding
to the admitting to what a person is accusing you of. תדע?
Teda? And indeed this seems to be the case because of the
continuation, דקתני סיפא, dekatani seifa, because at the end it says, אמרו
שנים אכלת חלב והוא אומר לא אכלתי פטור. Amru shnayim achalta chelev
vehu omer lo achalti patur. If two people come and say you
ate חלב chelev and he says I didn't eat it, he's still
פטור. patur. רבי מאיר מחייב. Rabbi Meir mechayev. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says it's חייב. chayav. אמר רבי מאיר קל וחומר. Amar Rabbi Meir
kal vachomer. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's a I forgot the
I forgot the a fortiori.
What happened to two people being believed?
שנים. Shnayim. So right, very strange, right? At first our assumption was
למה לי קרא? Lama li kra? If you say two people, it's
obvious that two people would be believed. Here it seems the סיפא
seifa tells us that in fact he's still פטור, patur, which already
you're getting to the point, which
is perhaps it's not an issue of נאמנות ne'emanut at all.
So he says which means then you do need your פסוק pasuk
to teach you that you know potentially
perhaps except that the fact is it seems to be the case.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir maybe needs it,
רבנן, Rabbanan, רבנן Rabbanan seem to be saying that we're in a
totally different paradigm, we're in a different paradigm entirely. We're not actually
talking about נאמנות. ne'emanut. We're not talking about reliability here. So he
says אמר רבי מאיר קל וחומר. Amar Rabbi Meir kal vachomer. אם
הביאו שנים לידי מיתה חמורה לא יביאו לידי קרבן הקל? Im heviu
shnayim lidei mita chamura lo yaviu lidei korban hakal? Right, if two
witnesses can cause you to get the death penalty, certainly they should
be able to cause you to get a קרבן, korban, which is
the reasoning that we said before. אמרו לו מה אם ירצה לומר
מזיד הייתי. Amru lo ma im yirtze lomar mezid hayiti.
They said, he is reliable to say I didn't eat it even
against two witnesses. Why? Because if he wants, he could say yes
I ate it and I ate it on purpose, at which point
he would no longer be חייב קרבן. chayav korban. In other words,
it's a it's like a מיגו migo of some sort. That's a
strange מיגו. migo. Yeah.
But it's but what the point is at the end of the
day, what brings a קרבן korban according to רבנן? Rabbanan? It's not
whether or not you actually sinned, it's whether or not you know
you sinned. And so if he still believes that he didn't sin,
or right, the idea is that he himself is the only person
who knows what his motivations were when he did the thing that
he did. And therefore for people to come and try and tell
him oh you did this, it's not going to be any good
because at the end of the day we need to know what's
going on in his personal psychological state.
Let the גמרא Gemara continue. רישא מאי טעמא קמחייבי רבנן? Reisha mai
ta'ama kemachayvei Rabbanan?
So in the initial piece, why do the rabbis why are the
rabbis saying that if he doesn't contradict
that he is that he has to bring a קרבן? korban? אילימא
משום דמהימן? Ilima mishum de'meiman?
If it's because that the עד ed is believed. והא תרי בעלמא
דאף על פי דקמכחיש להו אינהו מהימני והכא פטרי רבנן. Veha trei
be'alma de'af al pi de'kamach'chish lehu inhu meheimnei vehacha patrei Rabbanan. Right,
the exact case is reached a point that Michael brought. If it's
because that the witness is believed in that case, here's a case
where two witnesses who are believed in all cases even against the
protests of somebody are not believed. So it appears the rabbis are
not working in the realm of נאמנות, ne'emanut, of reliability. אלא לאו
משום דאשתיק? Ela lav mishum de'ishtik? Rather it's because this person actually
was silent. ושתיקה כהודאה דמיא. Ushtika ke'hoda'ah damya. And
and being silent is the equivalent of agreeing that what the person
said is true.
אלא סברא היא. Ela sevara hi. Alright, we're going to abandon the
the פסוק, pasuk, and we're going to try to learn this from
logic. מדידהוה אחתיכה ספק של חלב ספק של שומן ואתא עד אחד
ואמר ברי לי דשומן הוא דמהימן. Mididehava achaticha safek shel chelev safek
shel shuman va'ata ed echad ve'amar bari li deshuman hu de'meiman. So
we have a law that the גמרא Gemara knows, which is if
we have a piece of meat, this is very interesting, just
parenthesized, there are feminist scholars of the תלמוד, Talmud, Charlotte Fonrobert comes
to mind at Stanford, who talk about the metaphors that they use
or the the way that the תלמוד Talmud sort of discusses the
status of women.
Here would be a good case. She talks a lot about the
in the first chapter of מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah about comparing a
woman to a מקוה, mikvah, comparing a woman to various other pieces
of furniture as it were. Here talk about comparing a woman to
a piece of meat. We are literally saying the דין din of
a woman of the wife in this case is the same דין
din as this piece of meat.
So we say, right? Meat,
so we say at the case where we have a piece of
meat that might be חלב Chelev but it might be כשר Kosher
meat. And a single witness comes and says I know for sure
that is כשר Kosher meat, that witness is believed. So we say
מי דמי? Mi dami? Is that really does that really resemble the
case that we're talking about? התם לא איתחזק איסורא. Hatam lo itchazek
issura. In that case we had a doubt, we didn't know if
it was a כשר Kosher piece of meat or חלב. Chelev. הכא
איתחזק איסורא דאשת איש. Hacha itchazek issura d'eshet ish. In this case
we know that this woman was married, it's just a question of
whether her husband is dead or not. ואין דבר שבערווה פחות משניים.
V'ein davar she-be'erva pachot mishnayim.
And certainly in a case where we're going to have a problem
with adultery, a problem with sexual crimes, we shouldn't have less than
two witnesses.
Is these two separate objections?
No, I think that they are related. In other words, once we
say איתחזק איסורא דאשת איש, Itchazek issura d'eshet ish, right? We know
that this woman was married, and that case is a case of
עריות Arayot and therefore we say we shouldn't be dealing with a
case of עריות Arayot פחות משניים. Pachot mishnayim.
No, but even the case of חלב Chelev if it's איתחזק איסורא,
Itchazek issura, the עד אחד Ed echad would not help.
Yes, okay. הלא דמיא, Ha la damya, this is
not this is only similar to אלא חתיכה דודאי חלב, Ela chaticha
d'vadai chelev, a piece of meat where we know that it's חלב,
Chelev, ואתא עד אחד V'ata ed echad and a single witness came
ואמר ברי לי דשומן הוא, V'amar bari li d'shuman hu, דלא מהימן.
D'lo meheiman.
So it's more similar to a case where we know that something
is not כשר Kosher and now a single witness comes and tells
us it's כשר. Kosher. So we say מי דמי? Mi dami?
Yeah, but so we do say that like, you know, if a
woman if a single witness comes and says I saw that your
husband died that you do believe him.
Well we're looking for the origin of that. We're trying to figure
out how is it that we're allowed to, because we can't say
מי דמי
Mi dami if it's דלא מהימן D'lo meheiman in the case of
חלב Chelev it isn't, it is.
Except we said we said we said we tried to say this
is a case of a ספק Safek a piece of ספק, Safek,
a ספק חלב ספק שומן. Safek chelev safek shuman. And we said
no, it doesn't resemble ספק חלב ספק שומן. Safek chelev safek shuman.
In fact it resembles a case of ודאי חלב Vadai chelev where
it's not מהימן. Meheiman.
But it is מהימן Meheiman in the case of in our case.
That's why that's that's what, meaning
it's comparable to that but we don't get the same conclusion.
Okay, so this this logical argument does not take us down the
road that we want to take, right? That statement is in is
arguing against the
the logical argument, the סברא Svara that they're trying to bring, that
this woman that this there should be some kind of logical argument
that that the עד אחד Ed echad is נאמן. Ne'eman. So back
to the person who thinks that there is a logical argument, they
say מי דמי? Mi dami?
It depends on who who the woman, if the woman was pure,
meat was כשר. Kosher.
Oh I see, in the case of, right, in the case of
how do you פסקן Pasken in cases like
this? Yes, in in the cases of true פסק Psak that that's
absolutely the case.
If she if not pure, she she cannot pure herself, I don't
meat was...
Yes, this this what, yes that's right.
If a woman came with a chicken, asking a שאלה, She'ela, and
if she was pure the chicken's כשר. Kosher.
That's right, you find a way. So the גמרא Gemara says מי
דמי? Mi dami? But your case says back to the the doubter,
your case doesn't resemble isn't resemble this either. התם אפילו בי מאה
לא מהימני. Hatam afilu bei mea lo meheimni. If we know we
saw the piece of חלב Chelev come off of the animal, no
matter how many witnesses come and say oh I know that that's
a כשר Kosher piece of meat, we still don't believe them because
we know it's a
a piece of חלב. Chelev. So we say הכא כיון דכי אתו
בי תרי מהימני. Hacha keivan d'ki atu bei trei meheimni. And in
the case of a witness, certainly if two witnesses came in case
of a woman, certainly if two witnesses came and said her husband
is dead, we would believe them. So חד נמי מהימן. Chad nami
meheiman. מידי דהוה אטבל הקדש
וקונמות. Midi d'hava a-tevel hekdesh v'konamot. So let's believe a single witness
also just as we do in cases of טבל, Tevel, הקדש, Hekdesh,
and קונמות. Konamot.
דוב, Dov, if you don't mind a little digression? Yes.
This case of where where of איתחזק איסורא? Itchazek issura? Uh-huh. Like
what kind of חזקה Chazaka is it that is not contradicted by
a hundred witnesses? Like what's the source of what kind of source
of information can there be other than witnesses?
If you see it if you see a piece of meat that
you know you saw it come off the animal. Who's who? What's
that?
Who are you? You, דוב.
Dov. Yes, and you... Okay. And you see a you have a
piece of meat that somebody cut off the kidney of an animal,
okay, and you have it you know that that piece of meat
is חלב Chelev
because you saw it yourself.
Right? No matter how many many witnesses come and say no no
we recognize this piece it's got this color it's got this whatever,
right? Or we whatever you know you saw that it's חלב. Chelev.
Right? You're not allowed to eat that to eat that piece of
meat. Even if someone else... so other people would be other people
would
be personal knowledge versus witnesses.
Yes, that seems to be the case here, right? It's the case
of what it means for something to be ודאי חלב. vadai cheilev.
The only thing I can imagine from ודאי חלב vadai cheilev is
if, if you yourself actually know that it's חלב. cheilev.
Okay so the fact, so if it's in the butcher case at
a butcher shop, that's not...
Right. You'd be, so that's what Michael said, right? You can't eat
it, but all the rest of us could eat it if a
hundred witnesses came and said that it's...
Okay, so we say there are cases, there are three cases where
we do allow a single witness to change our mind about things,
which is cases of
טבל, tevel,
things that have
not had the tithes removed from it, הקדש, hekdesh, a case of
something that we may have made holy to the Temple, and קונמות,
konamot, particular kinds of vows.
So we say האי טבל היכי דמי, hai tevel heichi dami, what's
the case of טבל? tevel? Just to lay it out, apparently we
have
a basket of grain and we think that maybe it's טבל tevel
and somebody comes and tells us, no, no, I know that this
basket is actually מתוקן, metukan, that somebody, that the people who own
this have already taken the tithes from this. Apparently we're allowed to
believe that single witness in that case. So we say אי דידיה,
ei dideih, if the person who comes and tells you is the
actual
owner,
משום דבידו לתקנו, mishum d'beyado l'takno, because you can, you can trust
them because they can take the tithes at any moment, right? It's
their right, so since they could have done it at any time,
you assume that if they're telling you that they did it, they
did it. אלא דאחר, ela d'acher, rather it must be that the
witness is coming to talk about somebody else's,
somebody else's טבל. tevel. מאי קסבר, mai kasavar, what's the, what's the
שיטה? shita? So we go, we reference a מחלוקת machloket elsewhere. The
מחלוקת machloket says, can you take from your own
property and take tithes on somebody else's property? Let's say I take
a couple of dollars and I say that basket that belongs to
David is actually, even though he hasn't taken tithes from it, I'm
going to take tithes from it on his behalf, and therefore people
are eating of it, it's okay. So we say אי קסבר התורם
משלו על של חבירו אינו צריך דעת בעלים, ei kasavar hatorim mishelo
al shel chaveiro eino tzarich da'at be'alim, that you can actually take
tithes for somebody else based on your own
property, אינו צריך דעת בעלים, eino tzarich da'at be'alim, if you can
do this without the
owner knowing, משום דבידו לתקנו, mishum d'beyado l'takno, that, the reason that
one witness is permitted is because that one witness is almost like
the owner now. He himself could, could take the tithes on that
טבל tevel at any moment.
I'm sorry, just, just to understand what we're trying to get here.
So we're not saying necessarily that in all cases a single witness
is נאמן? ne'eman? Not anymore. Right. We're saying that, you know, maybe
in this case it would be because it's not like the חלב
cheilev case, because the חלב cheilev case is, you know, a fact
is a fact, whereas over here, you know, it's more fluid because,
you know, she can, it was her husband and not be married
anymore, right? Or maybe like in some other cases, right, like טבל,
tevel, הקדש, hekdesh, or...
That's it. We're trying to say that the model of, of the
woman being in, who's, with a single witness who comes and tells
her her husband is dead is not like the model of חלב.
cheilev. It's more like the model of טבל tevel or הקדש hekdesh
or קונמות. konamot.
And it wouldn't necessarily be the case like, you know, in money
cases that we'd believe a single witness?
No, that's correct.
Like we're not going there.
That's right.
So we say okay, if you can fix it without, without the
owner's knowing, then okay, the witness could fix it, could fix it
at any time and therefore we believe him. ואי קסבר צריך דעת
בעלים, v'ei kasavar tzarich da'at be'alim, and if it's because, if we
say you can't do it unless the owners actually know, ואמר אנא
ידענא ביה דמתקני, v'amar ana yadana beih d'mitkani, and the עד ed
says,
no, I know that this stuff is okay,
הא גופא מנא לן? ha gufa m'na lan? Okay, so if that's
the case we're talking about, where a single witness comes and tells
you that a basket that you think is טבל tevel is now,
is actually has had the tithes removed, where do you get that
from? We're back to square one. Okay,
if you, maybe you can say that the woman is the same
as that case, but what's the origin of the basket?
הקדש hekdesh we're going to have the same issue. הקדש נמי. hekdesh
nami. Charlie, you're giving me a weird look.
Well, I mean, Shabby, I could, I could come say, hey look,
you don't need to worry about it, I took the tithes.
If, so if, if you can do it without דעת בעלים, da'at
be'alim, then I can believe you because if you haven't done it,
you could still do it, right? But if you are just testifying
about yourself and now the question is,
since when, since when can
we... Not clear the
גמרא Gemara that we can, that we can trust such a, such
a testimony.
We're now at הקדש. Hekdesh. So you made something הקדש, Hekdesh,
and now you want to and now you want to or you
think that something is הקדש Hekdesh and you want to use it,
right? So you want to see if somehow maybe it got out
of being הקדש. Hekdesh. Maybe somebody went to a חכם Chacham and
said, "Oh, I didn't mean to make this נדר, neder, I didn't
mean to make this vow on this thing, I meant to make
it on something else" and so on. So a single witness comes
and says, "That's okay, that thing is not הקדש." Hekdesh. That's what
we're talking about. So we say,
הקדש נמי אי קדושת דמים, Hekdesh nami i kedushat damim, משום דידיה
לפדותו. mishum deyadei liftoto. At any time you can say, okay, it's
not... I said it was going to be the whatever, ten thousand
dollars that's in my savings account, but actually I'm going to make
it the ten thousand dollars that are in my checking account, because
you're a very wealthy person, I guess.
So you could always fix it. You could always change it. So
since you could always change it, then we also say that, okay,
so then in that case, we believe you if you say
that that's what happened. אי קדושת הגוף, i kedushat haguf, if we're
talking about you said this animal is going to be... is going
to be הקדש Hekdesh and I'm going to bring the קרבן korban
from it,
דידיה, didia, if it's his own animal, משום דידיה לשיאולי עליה. mishum
deyadei leishalei alei. He could always go to a... the same person
could always go to a חכם Chacham and get this animal cleared
of הקדש. Hekdesh.
אלא דאחר, ela de'acher, rather it must be talking about somebody else's,
ואמר ידענא ביה דאיתשאל מאריה עליה. ve'amar yadana beih de'itshal marei aleih.
And the witness says, "I know that the owner has cleared this
animal from being הקדש Hekdesh by going to a תלמיד חכם." talmid
chacham. So we say, היא גופא מנלן? hi gufa minlan? Where do
we get that from that you can trust a single witness for
that? In other words, each time we come back to the place
where we start to actually resemble the case of our women, we
say, that's where the logic starts to fall apart. We can understand
all of those cases in various scenarios, but not the scenario that
would actually resemble our case. And one more, קונמות נמי, konamot nami,
the case of
making vows of various sorts. Let's say you make a vow that
a piece... a particular piece of fruit or something is אסור assur
to you. So
there's a question
of what exactly is the meaning of that vow. How do you
say, "Okay, I'm going to dedicate this fruit to the Temple," is
that what the נדר neder is about, or is it simply to
say it's אסור? assur? So we say, אי קסבר יש מעילה בקונמות
וקדושת דמים נחתא להו,
i kasavar yesh me'ilah
bekonamot vekedushat damim nachata lehu, so if it's about the fact
that when you make a נדר neder what you're actually doing is
dedicating something to the Temple, so then that means there's a certain
amount of money that you have to pay to the Temple. So
we say, משום דידיה לפדותו. mishum deyadei liftoto. So what you could
do is you could just say, "Okay, I'm going to give this
apple costs however much, twenty-five cents, I'm going to put the twenty-five
cents... I'm going to say this quarter now is the thing that
is קודש kodesh and the apple is
okay." ואי קסבר אין מעילה בקונמות ואיסור בעלמא הוא דרכי להו אכתפיה,
ve'i kasavar ein me'ilah bekonamot ve'issur
be'alma hu derachi lehu akatfei, and it's just a simple he's made
something אסור assur to
himself, דידיה, didia, if it's his own the thing that he himself
made the oath on, משום דידיה לשיאולי עליה. mishum deyadei leishalei alei.
And in that case he could
go to a חכם Chacham and get it cleared out. אלא דאחר,
ela de'acher, rather it must be that somebody is talking about something
that's an oath that somebody else made, ואמר אנא ידענא דאיתשאל מאריה
עליה. ve'amar ana yadana de'itshal marei aleih. And he says, "I can
tell you that the owner has made this thing מותר." muttar. We
should just point out that it wasn't clear exactly. קונמות konamot can
be two things. קונמות konamot can be to make something אסור assur
to you, but קונמות konamot can also be to make your property
אסור assur to other people. And that seems to be the case
here. That what this person did was he said, you know, some
particular piece of my property is now אסור assur to the whole
world, and the question is: how did he do that? Did he
do that by making it some kind of הקדש, Hekdesh, or did
he do that because since it's his property, he can say who
has rights to it and who doesn't?
So we say, היא גופא מנלן? hi gufa minlan? Where do we
get that logic? אלא אמר רבי זירא. ela amar Rabbi Zeira. So
now, I don't know if you've noticed, but everything we've had up
to this point has been anonymous. All of this is sort of
the back and forth of the סתמא דתלמודא, stama d'Talmuda, and now
we finally have a named statement. An אמורא Amora comes forward. And
so we often say when an אמורא Amora says this, when we
have... We often say that the name statements seem to be earlier
than the anonymous material which suggests that the Talmud knew the answer
when it started going through this whole process.
And he says, מתוך חומר שהחמרת עליה בסופה הקלת עליה בתחילה. Mitoch
chomer she'hichmarta aleha besofah hekaltah aleha betechilah. He says because it is
so, the consequences are so dire, we don't have to make life
so difficult for her in the beginning, right?
Since she knows that she's taking a huge risk if she gets
married on the basis of the testimony of one witness, we assume
that she will wait until she really knows that her husband is
truly dead before she goes off and gets married, and therefore we
can allow ourselves to be מקילין mekilin on the testimony of a
single witness. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא תחמיר ולא תקל, Lo
tachmir velo takal, right?
Do me a favor, I don't know, do me a favor and
just leave it be. Don't make it easy in the beginning and
then you won't have such dangerous consequences at the end with all
ממזרים mamzerim מזה ומזה mizeh umizeh and no כתובה ketubah and none
of the things that she would expect to get from her husband.
I don't need,
I'd rather have nothing than have to take the bad with the
good.
So we say, משום עגונא אקילו בה רבנן. Mishum aguna ikilu bah
rabanan. At the end of the day, we boil back around to:
no, we have to go easy on her at the end, otherwise
she's going to be an עגונה aguna for the entire, for her
entire life.
Is this her area over here?
Yes, right, this would be her area although I was just going
to point out that
this
kind of עגונה aguna is a slightly different kind of עגונה aguna
than the crisis we're dealing with today and one that's actually far
easier to solve. Or far easier.
It is halakhically we've come up with much better solutions for this
kind of עגינות aginut where a woman's husband disappears
than the kind of עגינות aginut we're dealing with with recalcitrant husbands
where we know they're alive and they're just not agreeing to give
the גט. get.
There were a lot of cases of 9/11 after that for this.
That's right. 9/11 was an important place for this.
Also to speak for Rivkah, but I think she would take a
different, she would have a different opinion that there are plenty of
halakhic strategies that just are not put to use. Correct.
I shouldn't have said... so I... that's correct. I didn't mean to
say what is the proper way of doing it. I meant to
say what is the way that has actually been put to use.
Correct.
We now get to the next part of the משנה Mishna which
says when her husband comes back, תצא מזה ומזה. tetze mizeh umizeh.
She has to be divorced from both her second husband and from
her first husband, וכולי. vechulei. אמר רב. Amar Rav. רב Rav said,
לא שנו אלא שנישאת בעד אחד אבל נישאת על פי שני עדים
לא תצא. Lo shanu ela she'niset be'ed echad aval niset al pi
shenei edim lo tetze.
Rav
said what we're talking about is a case where a woman got
married with one witness. But if she got married with two witnesses,
then she doesn't need to leave her second husband. She can stay
with the second husband. מחכו עליה במערבא. Machku aleha bema'arava.
In ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they thought this was the funniest thing
in the world. They laughed about this.
But is he going to explain his reasoning?
The גמרא Gemara is going to have to explain it because in
מערבא Ma'arava they're laughing, you can't just let them laugh. We have
to try to figure out what's going on. So, in...
I mean, the reasoning, just preliminarily we can say the reasoning seems
to be
תרי עדי Trei edim believed? Yeah.
That she got married on the basis of two witnesses. Two witnesses
create a reality, a fact on the ground. Since she got married
with two witnesses, that means that no matter who comes back, even
the husband? That's right. Her marriage stands. So that's exactly what they
laughed about this. This is reminiscent to me about what Dov said
a little earlier which is who knows, right? When two witnesses come...
what would be a case of חזקת איסור chazakas issur where two
witnesses wouldn't be able to turn it around? It would have to
be a case where somehow you know yourself or something like that.
So מחכו עליה במערבא. machku aleha bema'arava. They laughed about this in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אתא גברא וקאי. Ata gavra veka'i.
The man comes and he's standing in front of you. ואת אמרת
לא תצא? Ve'at amart lo tetze? And you're telling me that she's
going to stay with the second husband even though you can see
the first husband right in front of you? לא צריכה, Lo tzericha,
says the גמרא. Gemara. We do need Rav's statement. דלא ידעינא ליה.
Dela yad'ina leh. We don't recognize him. Somebody is coming and claiming
to be the long-lost husband and we don't recognize him and we
don't know if it's him.
But if we did, then Rav would...
If we did, presumably then we'd fall back onto... we'd be in
the position of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. We'd say oh, he's come,
he's here, she definitely has to leave her
second husband.
But she can't go back to the first husband either?
So we'll talk about that. Rav seems to think something different about
that.
But yes, the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* seems to lay out that she
shouldn't, she shouldn't go to either, although again, in a case of
two witnesses, the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* says, there's a משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*
seems to say that maybe she could. Right? That's the last part
of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. אם נישאת שלא ברשות shelo birshut *Im
nisset she-lo bi-reshut*. We'll see, we'll continue, we'll see in in רב
Rav *Rav*.
The whiteboard also doesn't recognize.
Let's hope he recognizes him okay on Monday.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: אידי דלא ידעינן ליה בחד מאי
תיכא *Idei d'la yad'inan lei b'ad mai tikha*. If you don't know
who this guy is, right? If he started out, if somebody just
comes and says, 'I am Haggai Reznikoff,' you know, 'Here I am,
I've returned after my long, my long absence,' and it doesn't look
like me and you don't, you don't recognize this person, why on
earth would you make her leave her second husband for that? So
he says: לא צריכה *Lo tzerikha*.
Why would she make her leave her second husband in
the case of a single witness? Because, because רב Rav *Rav* said
she got married with a single witness, that's what the משנה *Mishnah*
is talking about, that she has to תצא מזה ומזה *Teitzei mi-zeh
u-mi-zeh*. Right? But if she got married with two witnesses, then we
say לא תצא lo teitzei, *Lo teitzei*. So we say, okay, well,
if you're talking about a case where we don't recognize the husband
who's come back, then why should she even, why should she leave
her second husband in a case of a single witness?
We say: לא צריכה *Lo tzerikha*. We actually do need, we still
need רב Rav, *Rav*'s statement, because what's the case? דאתו בי תרי
ואמרי אנן הוינן בהדיה מכי נפק ועד השתא *D'atu bei terei v'amri
anan havainan bahadei mikai nafak v'ad hashta*. 'We have been with him
from the time he left until this very moment.' ואתון הוא דלא
ידעיתו ליה *V'atun hu d'la yad'itu lei*. 'And it's your fault that
you can't recognize him. He's exactly the same person. We've been with
him, he hasn't gone anywhere, and it's you who've lost your memory
of what this person looks like.' דכתיב *Dekhtiv*.
We have cases of a single person who is not recognized. ויכר
יוסף את אחיו והם לא הכירוהו *Vayaker Yosef et echav ve-hem lo
hikiruhu*. 'Yosef knew his brothers and they didn't know him.' ואמר רב
Rav חסדא *V'amar Rav Hisda*. מלמד שיצא בלא חתימת זקן ובא בחתימת
זקן *Melamed she-yatza belo chatimat zakan u-va be-chatimat zakan*. 'He grew a
beard in the meantime.' My wife when I learned this.
That's not what that means, I don't think.
I think it means חתימת זקן *Chatimat zakan*.
החותם *Hachotam* is like an imprint. So, like you know, meaning חתימת
זקן *Chatimat zakan*... זקן *zakan*... no, like an imprint, like you know,
in other words, like his face is now capable of growing a
beard because in Ancient Egyptian society they didn't have puberty, they're all
clean-shaven. Ah, so, so, okay, so
what
I think it means is like his face has now physically changed,
like you know, a חותם *chotam* makes a seal, an impression, right?
Okay, or רב Rav חסדא *Rav
Hisda* may not have known that in Ancient Egypt they would all
clean shave.
Yeah, but I want to reconcile.
Okay, fine, that sounds like a great solution.
Well, also he's speaking Egyptian, which is a little bit different than
in the case of this husband came back, he probably wouldn't be
unrecognized because he's speaking in a different language.
Yes, although again, it doesn't go into the language so much here.
It just goes into the fact that, look, it does happen that
people do go away and you don't see them for a long
time and when they come back, you don't recognize them. Like you
know, they're all thin in college then you see them like 10
years later they're all fat and unrecognizable.
22 years and יוסף *Yosef* had none of his family members around
anymore who knew him when he was there originally. People die, people
move away.
Yes, I mean it... again, it appears to me that the reason
they're bringing יוסף *Yosef* and רב Rav חסדא *Rav Hisda* here is
just to indicate that it is clear that this could happen, that
you could end up... the witnesses come and say, 'It's your problem
if you don't recognize him, we've been with him, we know that
it's the same
guy.'
And... and these
things happen. סוף סוף *Sof sof*, says the
גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, you've convinced me.
But even in the case
that
you've, even in the case that you've laid out, תרי ותרי נינהו
*Trei v'trei ninhu*. We have two witnesses against two witnesses. Why two
witnesses against two witnesses? Two witnesses came and said the husband is
dead. Two witnesses come and say this man who is standing in
front of you is the husband. Okay, so we have two witnesses
versus two witnesses, that creates a ספק safek. *safek*. We don't know
what the status of this woman is. הבעל חייב אשם תלוי asham
talui *Ha-ba'al chayav asham talui*. Therefore, anytime... anyone who sleeps now with
this woman is a question of whether or not she is... she
is
allowable, to whether she's somebody's wife, and therefore they should have to
bring a קרבן אשם תלוי asham talui *korban asham talui*, the קרבן
*korban* for a ספק safek *safek*.
So the question back on רב Rav *Rav* is...
yes, it's a question on רב Rav *Rav*, right? Because רב Rav
*Rav* said לא תצא lo teitzei, *Lo teitzei*. So what kind of
לא תצא lo teitzei *lo teitzei* is that if he still has
to bring אשם תלוי asham talui *asham talui* every time they sleep
together? אשם תלוי asham talui. קאי *Asham talui kai*. אמר רב Rav
ששת *Amar Rav Sheshet*. רב Rav, ששת *Rav Sheshet* says, 'I have
the solution.' כגון שנישאת לאחד מעדיה *Kegon she-nisset l'achad me-adeha*. What happens...
What happened? She got married to one of the witnesses. This is
one of the interesting things, actually a little bit about like what
we talked about the חטאת, it's that אשם תלוי asham talui? is
not for somebody who knows that they didn't do something and somebody
comes to them and says, no, no, you sinned, you have to
go bring an אשם תלוי asham talui because I think you sinned.
אשם תלוי is for people who they themselves feel like they may
have sinned and they just don't know. So she married one of
her witnesses, then that would indicate that he himself doesn't feel any
doubt about the issue and therefore he doesn't have an אשם תלוי.
Very interesting, like you wonder why you would allow them to why
you'd allow her to marry one of her witnesses. That seems like
it's inviting all kinds of sort of conspiracy theories.
Yeah, it could be like a film noir. Yes, exactly.
So we say, okay, maybe the witness הבא עליה, haba aleha, right?
The man who sleeps with her doesn't have a problem, but היא
גופא באשם תלוי. hi gufa be'asham talui. So okay, the man doesn't
have a doubt, but she still has a doubt. So why doesn't
she have to bring an אשם תלוי? In other words, she still
has to leave the marriage. ואשם תלוי קיימא. ve'asham talui kaima. So
we say באומרת ברי לי. be'omeret bari li. She says, I am
certain that he is dead. And רש״י Rashi says the man came
and he showed her, the witnesses came and showed her signs that
convinced her completely that her husband was dead. You know, a piece
of jewelry. The husband never took off his wedding ring and they
brought the husband's wedding ring and she said, oh, well, you know,
if
he were alive, he wouldn't have taken this off, so that means
he must be dead. So we say אי הכי, i hachi, right?
What's the case is she married one of her witnesses and she
also knows for sure the husband is
dead. We say אי הכי מאי למימרא? i hachi mai lemeimra? Okay,
well, what's the חידוש chiddush of רב Rav in that case if
that's if we've gone that far? אפילו רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי לא
קאמר אלא שבאו עדים ואחר כך ניסת אבל ניסת ואחר כך באו
עדים הוא לא אמר. Afilu Rabbi Menachem Berabbi Yosi lo ka'amar ela
sheba'u eidim ve'achar kach niset aval niset ve'achar kach ba'u eidim hu
lo amar. So now the תלמוד Talmud gives a statement that we
won't understand until after we hear the ברייתא braita that it brings.
It says even the position of רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי Rabbi Menachem
Berabbi Yosi doesn't hold his strict position except in a case where
both sets of witnesses have already come and then a woman gets
married. But if she got married and then another set of witnesses
came,
then he doesn't say his position. That's what he says. Now let's
hear what the ברייתא braita says. דתניא, Detanya, as it says, שניים
אומרים מת, shenayim omrim met, two witnesses say the husband is dead,
ושניים אומרים לא מת, ushnayim omrim lo met, two witnesses say that
the husband is not
dead, שניים אומרים נתגרשה ושניים אומרים לא נתגרשה, shenayim omrim nitgareshah ushnayim
omrim lo nitgareshah, two witnesses say that this particular woman has been
divorced and two witnesses say she has not been divorced, הרי זו
לא תינשא. harei zu lo tinasei. She should not get married because
she is a ספק. safek ואם ניסת לא תצא ve'im niset lo
tetzei say the רבנן. Rabbanan. If she gets married, we say she
doesn't have to leave her
marriage. רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי אומר תצא. Rabbi Menachem Berabbi Yosi omer
tetzei. רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי Rabbi Menachem Berabbi Yosi says no, that's
not possible, she has to leave the marriage if she gets married
at that point. אמר רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Menachem Berabbi
Yosi, אימתי אני אומר תצא? eimatai ani omer tetzei? When do I
say that she has to leave the marriage? בזמן שבאו עדים ואחר
כך ניסת. bizman sheba'u eidim ve'achar kach niset. If first we have
the controversy between the two sets of witnesses, two witnesses say the
husband is dead, two witnesses say the husband is not dead. So
in that case if she then goes knowing that this is a
ספק safek, and she goes and gets married, so רבי מנחם ברבי
יוסי, Rabbi Menachem Berabbi Yosi, she can't get married under those circumstances,
she has to leave that marriage.
I'm sorry, but I'm getting this other question from earlier. You know,
we had this earlier, right? המביא גט ממדינת הים ואמר בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם לא ישא את אשתו, hamevi get mimedinat hayam ve'amar befanai
nichtav uvefanai nechtam lo yisa et ishto, right? So how do we
let this witness marry the woman?
So he said that's a case of a witness who brings a
גט, get, right? But we're not talking about a גט, get, we're
talking about עדות
מיתה. eidut mitah.
What's the difference?
The difference is whether or not you could, I mean, we're
relying on this witness, aren't we?
Yeah. So I don't know.
I'm not sure what the difference is
between the case of the גט get and the case of the
עדות אשה. eidut ishah. I think it's a good question, but I
don't have an answer for it.
Okay.
I
also
had,
I'm sorry, like you know this other thing that like sort of
like המענה על אשת איש והוציאוה מתחת ידו אף אם כנס יוציא,
hame'aneh al eshet ish vehotziu'ah mitacht yado af im kines yotzi, right?
Like you know
there's a rumor about you that you're sleeping with this woman and
then the husband divorces her and then you end up marrying her.
You really... Even if you did it, you should give her up.
So like, you know, so this seems like the same thing. Like,
you know, there's going to start a rumor, oh, that you fabricated
this whole husband death thing so you can marry her. It's going
to lead to this and you have to divorce her anyway, it
seems.
Perhaps.
In any case, what I don't have the answer to your question,
but what I do have is the statement that yes, it's extremely
odd that we would assume that she could marry one of her
witnesses. And then yeah, stay married.
Yes, that's very strange.
In any case, so
so we're talking about a case where the ספק safek. existed previously.
But אביי Abaye said ואחר כך באו עדים, ve'achar kach ba'u edim,
if two witnesses came and said your husband is dead and then
she went and got married and then two witnesses come and say
the husband is not dead, he says in that case even I
would admit that she doesn't have to she doesn't have to get
divorced. הרי זו לא תצא. Harei zo lo tetzei. Right? And we
say and in in מסכת כתובות Masechet Ketubot this סוגיא sugya comes
up. We set it up exactly the way רב Rav set it
up. That is to say, well we have a problem with אשם
תלוי and so on and we say, oh, she must be married
to one of her witnesses and she herself knows for sure that
her husband is dead. So we say okay, in that case what's
the חידוש chidush of רב, right? Even רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי Rabbi
Menachem be-Rabbi Yosi would agree with that. That's just a statement of
the תנאים. Tannaim. We all know this case. So we say כי
קאמר רב, Ki ka'amar Rav, we say רב would say this נמי
בזמן שבאו עדים ואחר כך ניסית nami bizman sheba'u edim ve'achar kach
nisset לאפוקי מדרבי מנחם ברבי יוסי. la'apukei mid-Rabbi Menachem be-Rabbi Yosi.
רב would actually say that even in a case where the there
the two witnesses are already disagreeing and so she's already this ספק,
safek if she marries one of her witnesses and she herself is
convinced that her husband is dead, that she doesn't have to leave
her second husband. And why is he saying this? Specifically to tell
us that the הלכה halacha is not like רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי.
Rabbi Menachem be-Rabbi Yosi. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri, there are people who
go a different way with using this ברייתא. braita. טעמא דניסית ואחר
כך באו עדים. Ta'ama denisset ve'achar kach ba'u edim. The reason that
רב says what he says is that she got married and then
the witnesses came. אבל באו עדים ואחר כך ניסית תצא. Aval ba'u
edim ve'achar kach nisset tetzei. Right?
Maybe רב's position is only if she got married before the second
set of witnesses came. But if a second set of witnesses came,
then she would have to leave her second marriage. כמאן? Keman? And
what is how is רב holding? כרבי מנחם ברבי יוסי? Ke-Rabbi Menachem
be-Rabbi Yosi? See? And רב actually holds like רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי
Rabbi Menachem be-Rabbi Yosi and the question of what's the חידוש? chidush?
דחידוש הלכה כרבי מנחם ברבי יוסי. De-chidush halacha ke-Rabbi Menachem be-Rabbi Yosi.
מותיב רבא. Motiv Rava. רבא Rava
brings a קשיא kashya on רב from a ברייתא. braita. מנין שאם
לא רצה דפנו? Minayin she'im lo ratza dafno? The case is a
case of a כהן Kohen who is married a woman who is
פסולה psula to him. Married a גרושה grusha or something like that.
And so we tell him that he has to divorce her and
he says I'm not going to divorce her.
So how do we know that if he says I'm not that
if he doesn't want to divorce her that we force him? We
beat him up
literally. תלמוד לומר וקדשתו, Talmud lomar ve-kidashto, you make him holy. בעל
כרחו. Ba'al korcho. He doesn't get the choice whether to be holy
or not. He has to be holy. Charlie?
And in this case it would not be considered a forced גט.
get.
I
mean, the case of מכפין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני makhpin oto
ad she'yomar rotzeh ani is a תלמודי Talmudic case, right? In the
modern day, now we really wish רבקה Rivka was here. In the
modern day people no longer go to the direction of מכפין אותו.
makhpin oto.
I don't know, I'm not an ethicist so I don't know if
מכפין אותו makhpin oto is a
would be a reasonable solution for the problem anyway, considering that there
are non-violent rabbinic solutions in the woodwork.
But
in any case, today we tend not to rely on מכפין אותו,
makhpin oto, although as you probably know there are some communities that
do rely on that. Yeah, there was that scandal.
Yeah. Actually I asked רבקה Rivka about it's just happenstance, I happened
to ask רבקה Rivka about the guy who was at the center
of that about three months before the scandal broke. And she told
me that she had actually worked with him at one point and
decided that
she didn't want
to, that the guy was no good and she avoided him. It's
a shame, right? Originally he had been helpful. She's not sure whether
he changed or not, but she clear after some point she clearly
got that he was no good and she better avoid him. Right.
And then three months later the scandal broke. Okay.
So in any case, yes, it would not be considered a forced
גט. get. So now we say היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What is
this case of the כהן Kohen who is married a woman who
is not appropriate to him? אילימא דלא נסית לאחד מן עדיה ולא
קאמרה ברי לי, Ilima dela nisset le-achad min edeha velo ka'amra bari
li,
if the case is our case, that is to say, a woman
whose husband went to מדינת הים medinat hayam and
Two witnesses came and said that her husband is dead and then
two witnesses came and said her husband is not dead, and so
on and so forth, right? If it's a case where she didn't
marry one of her witnesses and she didn't say I'm certain that
my husband is dead, צריכא למימרא? Tzricha lemeimra?
Do we need to say that we take her away from this
כהן? Kohen? I mean, it's obvious that there's a problem here. She's
a ספק. A כהן Kohen can't stay
married to her. אלא לאו דניסת לאחד מעדיה וקאמרה ברי לי Ella
lav deniset leachad medeha vekaamra bari li and
the ברייתא baraita tells us that we force her out. אלמא מפקינן
מיניה—therefore Alma mapkinan minei
at the end of the day we do remove her from the
second husband. So this is a קשיא kushya on Rav. Rav says
לא תצא, lo teitzei she does not have to leave. So we
say איסור כהונה שאני. Issur kehunah shani. For one thing, this isn't
your normal case of a doubtful marriage situation. This is a case
of a כהן. Kohen. A כהן Kohen has other reasons why he
shouldn't be married to a doubtful woman,
whereas
a regular ישראל Yisrael may not have that problem. ואי בעית אימא
מאי דפנו דפנו בעדים. Veiba'it eima mai dafnu dafnu beeidim.
Or you could say, what are we talking about to force him?
Again, literally דפנו dafnu means to hit him, but what does it
mean to force him? To force him with witnesses, right? רש"י Rashi
says what are we talking about? Before he marries her, we go
looking for witnesses who will muddy the waters and make it so
that he won't marry this woman, who will tell him that she's
actually married or her husband's actually alive, all kinds of things like
that. And therefore we force the issue by creating a situation where
he's not able to marry her ahead of time. But if he
goes through with it and does marry her, we don't remove her
from him. ואי בעית אימא כשבאו עדים ואחר כך ניסת ורבי מנחם
ברבי יוסי היא. Veiba'it eima keshebau eidim ve'achar kach niset veRabbi Menachem
bar Rabbi Yose hi.
Or maybe what's the case here? The case is where we already
have two witnesses versus two witnesses, so she's a ספק and this
ברייתא baraita is according to רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי Rabbi Menachem bar
Rabbi Yose and Rav holds differently. רב אשי אומר. Rav Ashi omer.
I have to say this is the only time I've ever seen
רב אשי
אומר, Rav Ashi omer,
usually it would be רב אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar.
But I don't know, have to pay attention to it in the
future. מאי לא תצא דקאמר רב? Mai lo teitzei deka'amar Rav? What
does Rav mean when he says she will not go out? לא
תצא מהיתירה הראשון. Lo teitzei meheterah harishon.
She does not go out from being permitted to her first husband.
In other words, when two witnesses come and say her husband is
dead and then she goes and gets married, and then the husband
comes back, she is not אסורה asurah to that first husband, she
can go back.
She is
אסורה asurah to the second husband. In other words, Rav Ashi says
whatever you're thinking about לא תצא, it's not לא תצא from the
second, it's לא תצא from the first. That's what Rav means.
But meanwhile any children she had from the second one are ממזרים?
mamzerim?
Yes, I think that's the way it would end up being because
the second one was not a marriage, she was basically a זונה.
zonah.
So we say הא אמרה רב חדא זימנא. Ha amrah Rav chada
zimna. But Rav says this somewhere else. Where? דתנן, Detnan,
as it said in our משנה, ניסת שלא ברשות מותרת לחזור לו.
Niset shelo birshut muteret lachzor lo.
If she gets married without permission, which we understand to mean if
she gets married with two witnesses, meaning she doesn't need the permission
of בית דין beit din because she has evidence that the husband
is dead, she can go back to the first husband because she
was considered to be אנוסה. anusa. She didn't have a choice in
the matter, she really thought that he was—it was a fact for
her that he was dead. ואמר רב הונא אמר רב הכי הלכתא.
Veamar Rav Huna amar Rav hachi hilcheta. So
we have a statement that Rav says the הלכה halacha is like
this statement that if she did it שלא ברשות with two witnesses,
she can go back to her first husband. So in that case,
why does Rav
need to say a second time that she can go back to
her first husband? So we say חדא מכללא דחברתה איתמר. Chada miklala
dechavreitah itmar. Actually, one follows from the other. Since הלכה halacha is
like this end of the משנה, therefore she does not—she is not
לא תצא מהיתירה הראשון, lo teitzei meheterah harishon, she does not leave
her initial היתר. heter.
אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. Now we have Shmuel's position.
לא שנו אלא שלא מכחשתו אבל מכחשתו לא תצא. Lo shanu ela
shelo machchishto aval machchishto lo teitzei.
What
are we talking about? We're only talking about a case where she
doesn't contradict the husband who comes back. In other words, the husband
comes back and says here I am, and she says to him
you're not my husband, I'm married to this guy. If she does
say that, then she doesn't have to leave her second husband. So
the Gemara says במאי עסקינן? Bemai askeinan?
Wait, if she
does
say that, then she. Meaning she stays married to whoever she's married
with presently. That's what it seems like. Okay the husband comes back.
The husband comes back and she contradicts him and says you're not
my husband I don't know who you are. The case of לא
ידעתו. Lo yadato. Right?
So apparently שמואל Shmuel says if she stands up and she says
I don't know you you're somebody else she can stay with the
second husband.
And there are two witnesses
letting her get married in the first place presumably although perhaps not.
שמואל Shmuel remember is not referring to a case of רב, שמואל
Shmuel is referring to our משנה. Our משנה is talking about צא
מזה ומזה. Tzet mizeh umizeh.
Right no that's what I was asking so he's not... okay and
so but if she does say like oh my God that's right
you are he, then we wouldn't necessarily
permit her then to go back to her first husband.
No not according to שמואל Shmuel
because רב says you do right or according to רש״י.
Rashi. No רב says you do a hundred percent. Okay so we
said במאי עסקינן? Bemai askinan? This is where we get exactly the
questions of Michael of how many witnesses are there. אילימא בבי תרי?
Ilema bevei terei? If two witnesses come and say your husband is
alive, כי מכחשא ליה מאי הוי? Ki machasha leh mai havi?
She says the two witnesses know it's a lie, he's not alive,
he's dead.
Two witnesses, you can't contradict them. אלא בחד. Ela bechad.
What's going on? One witness comes back and says I'm sorry to
tell you your husband is... I'm sorry I'm happy to tell you
your husband is still alive.
So we say טעמא דמכחשתיה. Taama demachishatei. The reason that she
can stay with her second husband is that she contradicted
him. הא שתקה תצא. Ha shetaka teitzei. That sounds like she'd have
to go even on the basis of the testimony of a single
witness. והאמר עולא Veha’amar Ulla כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הרי
כאן שנים ואין דבריו של אחד במקום שנים. Kol makom she-he’emina Torah
ed echad harei kan shnayim ve-ein devarav shel echad bimkom shnayim.
This is really interesting conceptually to think about. עולא Ulla says anytime
the Torah allows you to get married or allows you to do
something on the basis of a single witness, the Torah has not
lowered the bar of testimony, the Torah has raised the status of
that single witness. And so what we're talking about is if a
single witness comes and says your husband is dead, that says עולא
Ulla is the equivalent of the testimony of two witnesses. Now a
single witness comes and tells her her husband is alive again. Well
that's only one witness.
But wouldn't you say the same thing then?
No because the Torah doesn't have a specific... a specific היתר heter
to rely on one witness who comes back and says the husband's
alive.
That's all the rabbis, not the Torah, that let her rely on
one witness.
How could the rabbis take an אשת איש eishes ish and allow
her to get married? There has to be something that permits them
from
some kind of Torah source. I'll just point out we didn't find
it... one allows them to rely on this single witness. At the
end of the day we assumed we said משום עיגונא Mishum iguna
they permitted it.
So you're saying... you're saying that the rabbis permitted it?
I think they have to... I think they have to understand if
they're going to do this that to some extent this is from
the Torah. That seems to be what's going on here with this
סוגיא. Sugya. So you're saying מעין קולא דרבנן?
me'ein kula de-rabbanan?
And therefore they're willing to rely on a whatever
a lesser היתר heter but at the same time we're treating it
as two witnesses. That's what seems to be going on here in
the סוגיא. Sugya.
No I guess I'm just saying כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד
אחד.
Kol makom she-he’emina Torah
ed echad. Yeah very odd way of saying it because he's like
the rabbis are the one who are letting her rely.
אין הכי נמי. In hachi nami. It's very odd.
So what we end up even though it's one witness against one
witness what you end up with is a case where because the
first witness has special status
that allows the...
that allows us to say that it's two witnesses against one witness.
במאי עסקינן Bemai askinan says the גמרא בפסולי עדות. Bipsulei edut. What
who are... there's
actually two witnesses who come and tell her her husband is alive
but who are the two witnesses? Two relatives, two women, two people
who are not allowed to give testimony. וכרבי נחמיה Ucherabbi Nechemiah and
it's according to the שיטה shita of רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah דתניא
Detanya רבי נחמיה אומר כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הלך אחר
רוב דעות. Rabbi Nechemiah omer kol makom she-he’emina Torah ed echad halach
achar rov de’ot. In all cases where the Torah permits the testimony
of a single witness it essentially cancels all the issue of פסול
עדות psul edut and you just go according to the majority opinion.
So in this case we have two people even though they're not
kosher witnesses we believe them against the one because one witness is
anyway not a normal kind of testimony. ועשו שתי נשים כאיש אחד.
Ve-asu shtei nashim ke-ish echad. Oh sorry. עשו שתי נשים באיש אחד.
Asu shtei nashim ba-ish echad. כשני אנשים באיש אחד. k'shnei anashim b'ish
echad. And they made and therefore in that case, they made two
women with a single male testimony witness like two men with a
single male witness, meaning we go according to the larger opinions.
ואיבעית אימא v'iba'it eima or you could say כל היכא דאתא עד
אחד כשר מעיקרא אפילו מאה נשים כעד אחד דמיין kol heicha d'ata
ed echad kasher mei'ikara afilu mei'ah nashim k'ed echad damyan or we
could say, no, actually we're not going to ever hold that פסולי
עדות psulei edut can be the equivalent, people who are not allowed
to testimony could be the equivalent of a single kosher עד. ed.
However, what's our case? הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, this is
the case, כגון דאתא אשה מעיקרא. k'gon d'ata isha mei'ikara.
So what happened? The initial עד, ed, the single, the first
witness was a woman. ותירוץ לרבי נחמיה הכי v'teirutz l'rabbi nechemia hachi
and we'll explain Rabbi Nechemia in the following way. רבי נחמיה אומר
כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הלך אחר רוב דעות ועשו שתי
נשים באשה אחת כשני אנשים באיש אחד. rabbi nechemia omer kol makom
she'he'emina torah ed echad halach achar rov de'ot v'asu shtei nashim b'isha
achat k'shnei anashim b'ish echad. So two women by against one woman
is the equivalent of two men against one man. אבל שתי נשים
באיש אחד כפלגא ופלגא דמי. aval shtei nashim b'ish echad k'palga u'palga
dami. But if you have two women and one man, that is
half and half. I think we'll stop there. We'll continue
with the next piece tomorrow.
That's the
I want to mention one other thing about those museums I think
is interesting. The mention of BCE, I go, it gives an
indication of this is probably a Jewish input.